Finding Aid for Orla Benedict Taylor papers, 1831-1943
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Orla Benedict Taylor papers 1831-1943
Taylor, Orla Benedict, 1865-1945.
4 linear feet
8681 Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan lawyer and banker, and alumnus of University of Michigan. Correspondence, essays, and newspaper clippings concerning the Detroit banking crisis of 1933; and biographical and genealogical information on the Church, Benedict and Mahon families; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Orla B. Taylor (donor no. 1682 ); other materials came from the University of Michigan Library (donor no. 1682 ) and George Stanley (donor no. 4552 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Orla Benedict Taylor was born in Fowlerville, Michigan on September 29, 1865. A graduate of the University of Michigan (B.A. 1886; LL.D., 1887), Taylor served as editor of The Oracle and The Chronicle while an undergraduate. He was also a member of Phi Beta Kappa and Sigma Chi fraternities.
Taylor entered practice in Detroit shortly after graduation, and very soon established himself as legal advisor for various property and business interests in the State. Among the notable cases in which he took part were the Ann Arbor Railroad Company vs. the Michigan Central Railroad Commission, and the Michigan Central Railroad Company vs. the Michigan Railroad Commission.
Mr. Taylor devoted his leisure time, especially after his retirement, to travel and study, historical research and writing, and the accumulation of historical and literary materials. Ever a loyal alumnus of the U-M, Taylor made many generous gifts to the University Library, including many valuable law books and a complete set of autographed letters and documents of Emperor Napoleon I and his marshals, as well as autographs of several of the Emperor's generals and cabinet members. He died December 1, 1945.
The Orla B. Taylor collection consists of correspondence, essays and other writings, and biographical and personal material. Many of the writings relate to banking in Detroit in the 1930s.
Subjects:
Banks and banking--Michigan--Detroit.; Benedict family.; Church family.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Depressions--1929--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.); Lawyers--Michigan--Detroit.; Mahan family
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Oracle (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Taylor, Orla Benedict, 1865-1945.; University of Michigan. Class of 1886.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--Anniversaries, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Contributors:
Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Burton, Clarence Monroe, 1853-1932.; Glass, Carter, 1858-1946.; McLeod, Clarence John, 1895-1959.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1831-1900 (Box 1)
    (include letters 1831-1832 from Benedict family members)
  - 1901-1929 (Box 1)
    (include letter of Clarence M. Burton, 1916)
  - 1930-1932 (Box 1)
    (include letter of William Warner Bishop, 1931 and letters of Henry M. Bates, 1932)
  - 1933-1939 (Box 1)
    (include letters of Carter Glass and Clarence J. McLeod, 1935 and letter of Henry M. Bates, 1936)
  - 1940-1943 (Box 1)
- Essays and other writings
  - Student essays, 1881-1882 (Box 1)
  - Essays concerning banking, 1932 and undated (Box 1)
  - Essay, "The Plot to Give the Cream of the Banking Profits of the Entire Country to the Customers of the New York Investment Bankers," undated (Box 1)
  - Essay on the banking crisis of 1933, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Essay entitled, "The Detroit Banking Tragedy of 1933" (Box 1)
  - Essay, entitled, "The Detroit Banking Tragedy of 1933" (Box 1)
    (rough draft)
  - Source material for banking essay, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Essay entitled, "The Story of the Detroit Bank Robbery ", 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Essay entitled, "The Story of the Detroit Bank Robbery" (Box 1)
  - Materials used in writings on banking in Detroit, 1933-1937, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Essay entitled, "Anno Domini 1925", 1925 (Box 2)
  - Papers used for "Anno Domini", 1917-1925 (Box 2)
  - Essay entitled, "Anno Domini 1927", 1927 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript for "Let Us Face the Facts", 1941, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Source material, for "Let Us Face the Facts", 1934-1940, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Essay entitled, "Rise and Principles of the Whig Party", undated (Box 3)
  - Essay entitled, "Lewis Cass, The Father of the West", undated (Box 3)
  - Essay entitled, "A Tourist in Java", undated (Box 3)
  - Essays, undated (Box 3)
- Biographical, personal, and miscellaneous
  - Autobiographical essays and notes, and genealogical information on the Benedict and Richard Church family, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Speeches, 1932-1941 and undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Inventory of the Library of Orla, B. Taylor, 1939-1941, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Papers concerning rare books and book collection, 1930-1932 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, concerning the banking crisis, 1933, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea., 1932 and undated (Box 4)
  - Transcript of U. S. Circuit Court of Appeals case resulting from the banking crisis, 1935, 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - Legal briefs, 1934, 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - Photographs1886and 1911 (Box 4)
    (include group portraits of Oracle (University of Michigan student publication) board, and of the 25th anniversary reunion of the University of Michigan Class of 1886)